<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A call in the universal spirit of Christ Jesus to all the wicked and impenitent sinners in the world, but more especially to the inhabitants of England, with the city of London, that they all may repent and turn to God, with all their hearts, before his wrath be more kindled, and his future judgements more appear to punish the inhabitants of the earth for their manifold horrible sins and transgressions : this came upon me to write, at the apprehension I had of that sudden fear which many people were suprised with, at the late earthquake, of what would befall them / [by] J.P.</title>
            <author>Parke, James, 1636-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32315</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12633274</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12633274</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64825</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55996)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64825)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1533:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A call in the universal spirit of Christ Jesus to all the wicked and impenitent sinners in the world, but more especially to the inhabitants of England, with the city of London, that they all may repent and turn to God, with all their hearts, before his wrath be more kindled, and his future judgements more appear to punish the inhabitants of the earth for their manifold horrible sins and transgressions : this came upon me to write, at the apprehension I had of that sudden fear which many people were suprised with, at the late earthquake, of what would befall them / [by] J.P.</title>
                  <author>Parke, James, 1636-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: James Parke.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Apocalyptic literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64825:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CALL, In the Univerſal Spirit of CHRIST JESUS, TO ALL THE <hi>Wicked and Impenitent Sinners in the World:</hi> But more eſpecially to the <hi>Inhabitants of England</hi> WITH THE City of LONDON, That they all may Repent and turn to God, with all their Hearts, before his Wrath be more kindled, and his future Judgments more appear to Puniſh the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Earth for their manifold horrible Sins and Tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <q>
               <p>This came upon me to write, at the apprehenſion I had of that ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fear which many People were Surprized with, at the late <hi>Earthquake,</hi> of what ſhould befall them.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>J. P.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 29.6.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Thou ſhalt be viſited of the Lord of Hoſts, with Thunder, and with Earthquake, and great Noiſe; with Storm and Tempeſt, and the Flame of devouring Fire.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 2.5.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>But after thy Hardneſs and Impenitent Heart, treaſureſt up to thy ſelf Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and Revelation of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgments of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and Sold by <hi>T. Sorole,</hi> at the <hi>Crooked-Billet</hi> in <hi>Holywell-Lane,</hi> in <hi>Shoreditch,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64825:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64825:2"/>
            <head>A Call in the univerſal Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, to all the Wicked and Impenitent Sinners in the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O! Fear, Tremble, Quake, and be Aſtoniſhed all ye Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Earth, and the Sea, unto whom Wo and Calamity belongeth, when you perceive or hear of the Lords ſhaking the Earth, and cauſing it to quake: Quake and Tremble, you that ſo much have ſcoffed at and contemned Quaking and Trembling at the Word of the Lord; now he is come terribly in his Judgments, and his Hand is lifted up in Judgment, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Earth to tremble at his dreadful preſence; and now his Judgments are in the Earth, that the Inhabitants thereof may learn Righteouſneſs; and be awakened to Righteouſneſs, by the many Warnings that the Lord gives this Generation of Evil-doers: Ah! quake and tremble in this hour of Gods Judgments, all you Proud and Wanton ones; you Stiff-necked and Rebellious ones; you Drunkards, Swearers, Lyars, and Curſed ſpeakers, who call God to Damn your Souls: Howle, howle, lament, lament with great Lamentation and Weeping, you Covetous ones, whoſe Hearts and Affections are ſet upon the Earth and Earthly things; and all you High-minded, Heady, Mockers and Deſpiſers of thoſe who are good, the Lord is much grieved with your Works of Darkneſs and great Abominations, which you continue in, filling up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your Iniquity, wherewith you cumber the Ground; and many appear as if they were fitted for Deſtruction. What know you how ſoon the Earth, which God hath ſhaken, may open upon you and ſwallow you up quick, and you come to periſh in your Sins; you who have in a high degree abuſed, and ſleighted the Lords Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, For bearance and Long-ſuffering to you-ward, and ſet at naught his Counſel, and would have none of his Reproof; you have deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Correction, refuſing to take Warning from the Lord God, who ſent many faithful Servants in his Name and Fear to warn you.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64825:3"/>
            <p>Therefore is the Righteous and Juſt God filled with Indignation, and come to plead with you in his Wrath and Vengeance; for Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is his, and he will repay it for the Evil and Wickedneſs done, and the Provocations wherewith the Inhabitants of the Earth have provoked God to wrath, for the Wrongs and Injuries againſt him, and one to another; for they that do wrong, ſhall receive for the Wrongs that they do; for God is no reſpecter of Perſons nor Parties, ſuch as every one ſoweth, ſuch muſt he reap from the righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth, who will do all men Right, and is Equal in all his Ways, and will be Righteous in all his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for evermore; when his Judgments are in the Earth, <hi>He will puniſh the Wicked in his Wrath, and vex them in his ſore Diſpleaſure;</hi> Although the merciful God hath a long time ſtrove with you by his good Spirit, and ſpared you, you will not always find it ſo, you Mockers at Quaking and Trembling at the Word of the Lord; now is the Lord making you to quake and tremble, and Pailneſs of Face and Horror muſt come upon you, and take hold of you ſuddenly.</p>
            <p>In the time of the EARTHQUAKE that came from God, the 8th Day of the 7th Month, 1692. in <hi>London,</hi> and many other places of this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> as well as other Countries, I ſaw in <hi>London</hi> many ſtruck at that preſent with a ſudden Fear of what might come upon or befall them, but few minded or rightly conſidered what they had done againſt Almighty God, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him to Anger and great Diſpleaſure: few were prepared to dye the death of the Righteous then, if Death had come upon them, which many feared greatly, when by the <hi>Earthquake</hi> ſo many Houſes in the City of <hi>London,</hi> with the Subborbs, were ſo terribly ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that many People were in expectation that their Houſes would fall down upon them, and others fearing that the Ground would have opened to ſink them down: I was in a great concernment and trouble of mind, for to hear and behold ſo many People in a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den expectation of the Death of their Bodies, whilſt unſenſible of there being dead in their Sins and Treſpaſſes, and ſo much unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for ſuch a final Change or Diſſolution of their outward man, they having not Repented of their Wicked Works, nor turned from the Evil of their Ways and Doings; and but few did I ſee that did turn their Minds towards the Lord, to feel him inwardly, or that did turn to him with all their Hearts, who by his great Power did ſhake the Earth outwardly; but few Rent their Hearts or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64825:3"/>their Ways, to turn to God, to look to him and wait upon him in Humillity, Reverence, and a Godly Fear; but many did I behold with ſtretched out Necks, and wanton Eyes, full of Pride, Vain Glory; and great Abominations were acted and committed in the Fairs at <hi>Smithfield</hi> and <hi>Southwork,</hi> and other places, as if God did not ſee, nor yet regard it. Ah! ſinful City and Nation! will you not ſee? will you not conſider nor lay theſe things to Heart, and Repent of your Crying Sins and great Abominations? Have not your Sins long cryed for Wrath and Vengeance to fall heavy upon you?</p>
            <p>O! that you would once come to hear &amp; obey the Voice of the Lord, and his threatning more Judgment and greater Calamity yet to come upon this City and Nation, if ſpeedily you do not Repent, and turn to God, from all your Tranſgreſſions and horrible Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions where-with he is ſo much provoked, and the Name of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, which you profeſs in Words, diſhonoured: Be ye all aſured, that the Judgments come and threatned, are not intended or ſent where they come, that any ſhould ſleight or diſregard them, but ſeriouſly to conſider them as ſo many Warnings from God, to the Wicked, for them to beware and take heed how they continue any longer in <hi>Sin, Rebellion</hi> and <hi>hard Heartedneſs</hi> againſt the Lord, leſt ſudden Deſtruction come upon you, that you will not be able to eſcape or flee from; you that declare your <hi>Sin</hi> as <hi>Sodom,</hi> what know you how ſwiftly the Deſtruction may come? O! remember and forget not that great Calamity which God Almighty of late brought upon <hi>Port-Royal</hi> in <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and how many Perſons in a moment periſhed, who may be were not more wicked then many in <hi>England</hi> are: O! why will you dye in your Sins, by remaining and abiding therein? Why do you retain your Hardneſs and Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of Heart, <hi>treaſuring up Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and the Judgment of the great Day?</hi> Will neither paſt, preſent, nor future Judgments alarum or awaken you? Will you ſtill ſtop your Ears, cloſe your Eyes, and harden your Hearts againſt the Lord? Have not many of you made your Hearts as an Adament? Are you not paſt feeling of what God intended for the awakening of you [out of your ſleep in <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Death</hi>] by that great and lamentable <hi>Plague</hi> and <hi>Fire</hi> in this City, and other Places? And is not <hi>War</hi> a heavy Judgment and Calamity where-ever it continueth long? Do you forget theſe things, and him that ſends or ſuffereth them to come in any Nation as he pleaſeth?</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64825:4"/>
            <p>O! tremble before the Lord! fear and dread his holy Name! Weep and howle for the Miſery that will come upon you ſpeedily, except you Repent, except you <hi>Ceaſe to do Evil,</hi> and <hi>Learn to do Well,</hi> in your time and day given you of God to Repent in; you <hi>ſeed of Evil-doers,</hi> and <hi>Children that are Corrupters,</hi> you <hi>Proud and Wanton Ones,</hi> you <hi>Stiff-necked and Rebellious Ones,</hi> you <hi>Drunkards, Swearers, Lyars, Whoremongers,</hi> and <hi>curſed ſpeakers,</hi> who call God to <hi>damn your Souls;</hi> Ceaſe from the Evil of your curſed ſpeaking, with all the Evil of your Ways and Doings: Repent, repent, and lament bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly for ſo often Pierceing, Villifying, and putting to ſhame the Lord of Life and Glory, Chriſt Jeſus, of whom you make ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion, but God ſearcheth and knoweth your Hearts; he heareth all your curſed blaſphemous Words, and ſeeth all your wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ways and Doings, whereby you provoke the Lord to wrath in a great degree of Wickedneſs, and foul Abominations acted and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted daily by many againſt the Lord, which will prove your Ruin, who do not take warning in your day and time, which is but ſhort, that God will allow you in this World; conſider the precious time God already hath afforded you, and call to mind the many Warnings you have had from God, through his faithful Servants, who have been ſtirred up in the Spirit of the Lord to pronounce his Woes and Judgments that ſhould fall upon the Wicked and Ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that did refuſe to take warning, and amend their ways.</p>
            <p>Conſider the Eternal Power of the Lord, which he is come to make known in the Earth, and in the Kingdoms of men, and over all he hath appeared to ſhake the Earth, and the Heavens, and all Nations; the Lord is come with Power and great Glory, to ſhake the Earth inwardly that is ſet in mans Heart, that it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the Heart, and ſo preparation may be in the Heart for the Lords appearance, to ſhake and remove that which is to be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, either inwardly or outwardly, and ſo People may come to the Knowledge of that which cannot be ſhaken with the Wind. O Earth, hear the Word of the Lord, and be aſtoniſhed ye Heavens, fear and dread before him all ye Nations of the Earth, and People of all Languages and Perſwaſions whatſoever, put no longer the Evil day afar off from you; you <hi>high</hi> and <hi>low, rich</hi> and <hi>poor, bond</hi> and <hi>free,</hi> that have <hi>cauſed the Seat of Violence to draw near;</hi> but put far from you all your <hi>Envy, Wrath, Bitterneſs</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> that ſo long hath had place in you, and hath been vented forth by many of you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64825:4"/>in Words and Actions againſt the appearance of the Lord, and that which is good, wrought by him in People, and in the World; which you ſhould have received, loved, and made choice of; you that have been and are Gainſayers and Oppoſers of the Appearance and Work of the Lord in your day, how have you called good evil, and evil good; put Light for Darkneſs, and Darkneſs for Light; Sweet for Bitter, and Bitter for Sweet, being unacquainted with the Eye-Salve, you cannot ſee aright into the things of God, nor diſtinguiſh them from the contrary: So <hi>you Juſtifie the Wicked,</hi> and would <hi>take away the Righteouſneſs of the Righteous from them,</hi> in your Blindneſs and Darkneſs that you are in; you have ſhut the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men, would neither enter in your ſelves, nor ſuffer them that would; Wo unto you whited Walls and painted Sepulchres, you appear beautiful to People, led into and kept in Darkneſs by you; but the Lord hath a Controverſie with you, you Idol-Sheepherds, who ſeek your Gain from your Quarter, but ſeek not the Ioſt Sheep, nor watch for the Soul: What account can you give of your Flooks which you are ſet over by men, and come to them as ſent of men, by whom you expect to be upheld? Are not many of your Flocks ſtarved, inſtead of being fed by you? Wherewith will you have to Anſwer the chief Sheepherd and Biſhop of Souls, Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters followed his Example, and fed the Sheep and Flock of Chriſt with Spiritual Meat, whom they had the overſight of; they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with great diligence to beget People that heard them, to God, that they might believe to the ſaving of the Soul; they did not turn any from, but to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, that they might love it, believe and walk in it, and become Children of it: But the Miniſters made and ſent by Man, have ſtumbled at, hated and rebelled againſt this Light, and ſome in their blind Zeal, without divine Knowledge, have contemned it, and incouraged there Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in their contemning of the Light of Chriſt, with which they are lightned, inſtead of turning People from Darkneſs to the Light of Life, which is the Cauſe why ſo many Nations, Peoples, Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds and Tongues yet ſit in Darkneſs, and under the region of the ſhadow of Death; and is the very Cauſe why ſo much Sin and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is ſpread over the Nations and Kingdoms of this World.</p>
            <p>Now are the Nations and People made Drunk, and ſtagger with the Whore's Cup, which ſhe hath put into their Hands to drink,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64825:5"/>which is the cauſe of there ſtumbling, and ſo much falling into the Pit, and why ſo many are ſtill ſnared and taken in that which is Evil, which by the Light of the Lord, the Light of the World, if they would turn to it, they might all ſee, and alſo avoid the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Evil in the temptation thereunto; and Peoples being in Darkneſs from this Light, is the cauſe why they do not ſee the Hand of the Lord, when lifted up in Judgment; 'tis but few will regard it before they feel it come heavy upon there Heads; altho' God be laying waſte Countries near us, and hath brought Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Earth, yet little is this laid to Heart by ſuch as at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent are ſpared from being ſo ſmitten, as ſome Countries have been and ſtill are, although poſſibly not greater Sinners, or more ſinful Nations then this, and yet ſorely puniſhed, waſted and ſpoiled by the preſent Hand of the Lord in Judgment. And if the People of this Nation go on in theſe grievous Sins and Treſpaſſes in Rebellion againſt God, he will certainly make them ſick in ſmiting of them, and put them in Fear, and Aſtoniſh them more and more, and lay their Honour and Glory in the Duſt, as he hath done in other Countries already; for how ſoon can he work Wonders to the Amozement of People and Nations! How ſoon can he lay a City on Heaps, and make a ſtrong Nation deſolate! What is a fenced City or ſtrong Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the Lord! when he in his Wrath entreth into Judgment, and pleadeth with People in his ſore Diſpleaſure: who can turn away his Wrath, or ſtop him from pouring out his Fury and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation? of which now the Inhabitants of this City and Nation are apparently warned by the late dreadful <hi>Earthquake,</hi> that you all might prepare for whatſoever may follow after it, and not periſh in your Pride, you Proud Ones, nor you Drunkards in your Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, nor you filthy unclean perſons in your Filthineſs and Debauchery, nor you Swearers, Lyers, Curſed Speakers, or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Ones, might dye in your Iniquity, nor any Evil which the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> even ſo horribly abounds with.</p>
            <p>And Repent, Repent all you <hi>Backſliders,</hi> who are revolted and ſlidden back from the Truth and Way of God; and love and have choſen the Way of the Wicked, which is Darkneſs, whereby you have been led, and have walked in Crooked Ways and By-pathes, and taken a liberty out of the Truth, and uſe it to your own and other Peoples hurt, and to the grief of the pure and holy Spirit of the Lord God eternal. I have Compaſſiod truly in my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64825:5"/>Heart towards ſome of you, that have a Sincerity remaining yet in you that know the Truth, and that no Lye is of it, how beit ye do not obey it, nor do after the pure Requiring of it; the Lord is angry with you, and will now plead with you in his Wrath, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you Repent and turn to the Lord and his Truth (with your Hearts) which you own and profeſs in Words, but are gone from the Life and Power of it. I know ſome of you began well to run in the Heavenly Race, that God by his Light ſet before you, and walked many Years on with the Flock of God, in the Path of the Juſt, in much Love, Unity and Concord; but afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in your Hearts from the Lord, his Truth, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Society of his People, and the Lord is much diſpleaſed with your Spirit of Seperation and Diviſion; and you Backſliders in heart ſhall be filled with your own Wayes and Evil Devices, your ſeperation will become Loathſome and an Abhorrence to all who are ſpiritually minded, and the longer you cleave to it, the worſe you will be, more hardened and ſeparated from God and your own good, being ſeperate from the Spiritual Fellowſhip and Communion of the faithful Flock of Chriſt Jeſus, the only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Redeemer: your ſhelter in the World and ſpirit of it will fail, when Calamity cometh upon Evil-doers, lean thereon never ſo much, and flee to it as much as you will for help, that help will ſtand you but in little ſtead, in this dreadful Day of God's Judgments, you will be judged; and your Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs puniſhed, by the great Judge of Heaven and Earth, who will Reward every man according to his Works.</p>
            <p>And all you great Pretenders to Reformation, who are out of the Life and Power of God, and are even ſtrangers to the divine Nature of Chriſt Jeſus, and know not him within you, the Hope of Glory, being Ignorant of the Life and Power of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which you do profeſs in Words, and outward Appearance; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, repent, the Lord hath a Controverſie with you; he will afflict and puniſh you yet more and more for your Sins, which you ſtand charged with, and are found guilty of in the Eye of the great Judge of Heaven and Earth, eſpecially you that have afflicted or helped forward the Afflictions the of Righteous and their Sufferings, as Evil Inſtruments in the hand of Satan, and by his Power; the Lord will afflict you, and ſorely puniſh you for your Iniquity and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64825:6"/>Wickedneſs, which you have acted and committed againſt the Lord and his Faithful Servants, when Perſecution did ariſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Word: How many pretend Preachers, or Miniſters of the Word, who have in their Malice and Envy raiſed or ſpread abroad falſe Reports againſt the Truth and Innocent Profeſſors thereof, to hinder the progreſs and ſpreading of the Truth of God, with their Lyes and Scandals againſt the Upright and the Juſt, who have been and are Doers of the Truth, and Faithful Followers of Chriſt Jeſus: Wo, wo, from him is coming upon you, you whited Walls and painted Sepulchres, and all you Daub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with untempered Morter, your inward Darkneſs and Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind is ſeen, that you are black inwardly; you whited Walls, your Whitening wherewith you white your outſide, is ſeen and diſcovered with the Light of Chriſt Jeſus; your paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves with the Prophets, Chriſt's or the Apoſtles Words, whilſt you are from the Life of the Word, and the ſafe Guidance of the Spirit of Truth, that will profit you little, nor cover you in the day of the Lords Wrath; God will ſhake and undo your <hi>Directory</hi> or <hi>Church-Faith,</hi> made by Men, whereby many have been kept from waiting for the Spirit of God, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Faith from him, which purifieth the Heart, whereby the only true God is pleaſed; you may appear fair and beautiful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, you Idol-Sheepherds, and principal of the Flocks, and gatherings together about worſhip of God, whilſt you do not Spiritually know him; the Shame of your Nakedneſs will ſhortly appear to the People, blindly led and deceived by you, and daubed over with your untempered Morter; howling and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lamentation will come upon you; many are deſiring Eye-Salve that they may ſee, and ſuch who buy that, will ſee, and more loathe and hate your Merchandize, how finely painted or daubed ſoever it may appear outwardly to Men, you Wolves in Sheeps cloathing, many do ſee, and Nations will abhor you and your diſhoneſt Gain, which ſo long you have ſought and gaped after: People comes to ſee your Deceit, and are aſhamed of your Covetous Practices, and your Works of Darkneſs.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64825:6"/>
            <p>I was conſtrained in the Spirit of the Lord God at this time to write, and upon the occaſion and Remembrance of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord already paſt, as well as what now is; with a deep Conſideration of what may yet proceed from God, as Threatned by the late Dreadful EARTHQUAKE, to call all People to Repentance and Amendment of Life ſpeedily, before it be too late; that thoſe ſo very grievous provoking Sins and Abominations now committed in this City and Nation, with many other Cities and Nations, may be Repented of, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hath kindled Gods fierce Wrath to that degree, which may bring great Ruin and Deſolation, if you continue therein; but if by Repentance, Weeping and Lamentation, you yet turn to God with all your Hearts, and put away the Evil of your Ways and Doings from before the Eyes of the Lord, from the higheſt to the loweſt, both Rich and Poor, Bond and Free; and not add Sin to Sin, as you have long done, and which now abounds almoſt every where; who knows yet but God may turn away his Wrath now threatned to be poured forth and executed. So Rent your Hearts, and not your Garments; be truly humbled under the Hand of the Lord, that is now lifted up in Judgment: Fear the Lord, and believe in his Name, ceaſe from Evil, and do Good in your time, for upon ſuch the Lord will have Mercy, they will not dye in their Sins when they dye, but will dye in the Lord the Death of the Righteous, and will have the Reward of the Righteous, even Everleſting Reſt and Peace: Which that you all may come to know and Inherit, and that it may go well with you in this World, and that which is to come, is the real Deſire of your Friend, and a faithful Well-Wiſher of all Mankind;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Parke.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
